let's now move to logical or virtual
addresses versus physical addresses
so let's say we write a program and we have
this instruction
equal b plus two
we know that when we run this instruction
inside the process
we will have some memory allocated and at
a specific address
we will have the variable a and at another one
we will have variable b and then we're going
to read b sum 2
and store that in the address of variable a
now the question here would be if the program
has not been
loaded yet into memory so it's just stored
in a disk what
is the compiled program?
so like the c program that runs this how does
this program
knows how are we storing the addresses of
a and b given
that we don't know yet where they will be
placed in memory
if we first don't actually start the process?
so how does the operating system support the
definition of
variables and memory if we don't know exactly
where the process
will be placed in memory until we actually
start running
it? and given that if we run the same process
n times we
can have n different locations at which
we are maintaining
the process in memory
well the operating system helps processes
and programmers
differentiating between logical or virtual
addresses and
the physical addresses the real ones that
you have in the
memory each process believes that its own memory
starts at address
zero and goes up to a certain address
okay so all addresses are relative to address
zero which
is the beginning of the process
this is the logical address
the physical one of course will actually start
at a specific
address and extend up to another address
for now
I'm just assuming that you take a big chunk
of main memory
and you place the entire process
so it's contiguous a contiguous set of addresses
we will see that this is actually not what
is really happening
but let's keep things simple for now
so what the operating system does is that
whenever a process
tries to access something that is in memory
it uses our
logical address and it says I want the address
3-4-6 for
example and then the operating system will
translate that
actually to the physical address in the real
physical main
memory at which the variable is maintained
the question is how do you convert logical
to physical addresses
efficiently getting help from the hardware?
something you can do
very simple
we will see again as I said that there are
more complicated
things happening
but for the discussion so far something simple
you can do
is to use a relocation register
so basically you take the address given by
the CPU
and since the process believes its first address
is zero
it basically means that it's giving you an
offset
you sum that the base address of each process
that is basically the conversion to the physical
address
you actually need to access in the main memory
so logical addesses will go from zero to max
in practice the real one we go from a certain
R to a
certain R plus max